This is Cairo's new administrative
capital, a brand new pre-planned city
next to Cairo built from scratch. It
looks just like New Cairo City, which is
another pre-planned city nearby also
built from scratch, or the 10th of
Ramadan City, or El Sheikh Zayed City,
or the 6th of October City, or October
Gardens. These developments are all big
blocks divided by large urban freeways.
They are car-centric and highly
segmented. Maybe I'm even underselling
it. Jesus Christ, look at all that road
capacity. There are roads literally
everywhere. Did they use City Skylines
for planning? And these developments all
look the same
because they were built by Egypt, right?
Well, not exactly. Here, take a look at
this place. It's called Dubai. You may
have heard of it.
Oh my god, it's a missile. What the
man? Thomas, look at this.
I'm actually so scared of being in JVC
right now, and I can see Oh, no, no, no,
no, no, no. Not meant to be happening
here.
Looks similar, doesn't it? It's also
[music] just big towers divided by large
urban freeways. Or here we have Jeddah
in Saudi Arabia. While the buildings are
not so tall and are more closely packed,
the underlying logic is the same. Urban
highways dominate and dictate the form
of the entire city. And with newer
developments, we once again see big
towers. Looking at these street layouts,
I'm starting to think they really just
used City Skylines to plan this out.
[music] So, these places look the same
because they're all Middle Eastern
dictatorships, right? Close, but still
not exactly. If we leave the Middle East
and take a look at Beijing, for example,
we see the exact same things again. Big
blocks divided by large urban highways.
How about Moscow? New developments there
are once again the exact same. Giant
towers next to massive urban freeways.
Did these countries copy each others
homework or something? Do they all share
the same save game in City Skylines? In
this series, the only areas where you
don't see the big towers next to urban
freeways are their older areas,
especially historical centers, which
look like normal cities for the most
part. But as soon as you step out of
those into contemporary developments,
it's suddenly all huge towers next to
wide roads. Shoutout to Turkmenistan
here, too, because their new
developments also look exactly like
that. And yes, they're also a
dictatorship. Man, I like Turkmenistan.
It's a funny place. Led by what is
basically a family clan, its former
dictator seemed to be under the
impression that he is a main character
of an anime, basically. This guy had
been up to some stuff. He erected a
golden statue for the country's
indigenous dog breed with a tasteful
curved screen built into the pedestal
playing videos on loop. He also erected
a golden statue of himself on a horse,
and also practiced weightlifting in
front of his applauding cabinet with a
golden weight bar.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> ANYWAY, HE'S DEAD NOW. HIS SON IS THE
NEW, quote unquote, president. I mean,
they call him that, but he's just
another dictator ruling over a
dictatorship. One that builds in the
exact same manner as other
dictatorships, like China, Saudi Arabia,
Russia, Egypt, the Emirates, and so on.
This begs the question of why. Why do
dictatorships look the same? Have they
been accidentally copying each other or
something? Well, turns out it is not an
accident at all. So, let's see the
reasons as to why. Number one, American
big tech is coming for us all. But
thankfully, ProtonMail is here to help.
ProtonMail is a privacy-focused
encrypted email service made to keep
your personal data safe. Not even Proton
can see what's in your emails, in fact.
This is in sharp contrast to services
like Gmail, where your emails may or may
not be fed into an AI data set.
ProtonMail is funded entirely by its
user base, so they have no incentive to
start selling off your data to third
parties like Google or Meta do. Speaking
of, migrating from Gmail is easy.
Migrating everything from your old
account takes about 30 seconds. And if
you also want to keep your old account,
that's no issue at all. With easy
switch, you can have your email
forwarded to your new Proton address
automatically. I also use this feature.
My business email is now with Proton,
but I kept my old Gmail just in case
something arrives there. When it does,
it gets forwarded to my ProtonMail
account. It's also important to mention
that Proton is a European provider.
Therefore, it's an alternative to
Silicon Valley big tech oligarchs and
their increasingly predatory AI-polluted
slop. So, thumbs up for ProtonMail.
Great service. Go to
proton.me/adamsomething
to get started with ProtonMail for free.
Their service is always free with
optional paid plans for additional
features and benefits. That's
proton.me/adamsomething.
Thank you for checking out ProtonMail.
And now, let's look at the real reasons
as to why dictatorships look the same.
The number one and most obvious reason
as to why dictatorships look the same is
the good old dick-measuring contest. Why
did Louis XIV expand Versailles into a
palace [music] and commission things
like the Mirror Hall? For the purposes
of dick-waving. Why did Charles Philip
commission Mannheim Palace in a way that
it has one more window than the Palace
of Versailles? For the same reason. And
so, Sheikh Mohammed has the Burj Khalifa
built [music] to be the tallest building
in the world. But then El Sisi comes
along with the Obelisco Capital, which
is supposed to be even taller than the
Burj Khalifa. You get the idea. And
dictators love playing this game. To
them, their countries are like City
Skylines maps, which they can then show
off to each other on Epstein's Island or
something. But this doesn't just happen
within the dictator and their peers.
Such monumental structures are also
meant to project power. If you were an
individual living in their countries and
wanted things like freedom or democracy,
you would probably feel more inclined to
voice your opinion if the government
operated out of a shed. But it doesn't.
It operates out of a giant scary
building that looks impenetrable from
the outside. And the city itself is
littered with their gigantic
megalomaniac structures, all looking
down at you. This affects people
psychologically. These buildings are
designed to make you, the citizen, feel
small and powerless. And this is part of
the reason why Moscow's skyscraper
district looks the way it does. It's as
if Sauron found oil and turned Mordor
into a petrostate, and then Rohan
started relying on Mordor petrochemicals
to function. Because what could ever go
wrong with that? Oh, the beacons are
lit. Gondor calls for aid. What? Oh, no,
that's just unfortunate. [clears throat]
I mean, yeah, Sauron is doing a
genocide. He's destroying the
Middle-earth world order. But what about
Rohan's economy? Oh, fine, Rohan will
answer. We will send to Minas Tirith
5,000 helmets. That should do the trick.
But another reason for such megalomaniac
projects is good old plain and simple
As a rule of thumb, the bigger the
building, the bigger your profit
margins. Not necessarily because the
project is more efficient or more
valuable, rather because it's very easy
to steal from big, long, opaque, complex
projects. If you build a single-family
home, anyone can track most of your
costs. A normal person can just look at
the budget, then do some Googling. Uh,
excuse me, the project says this window
costs $5,000, but I found the same
window for 2,000 at six different
stores. Oh my. That sounds a lot like
seditious conspiracy against the
government to me. But with such massive
projects, where there are dozens of
companies and thousands of workers, it's
very easy to overprice things, then hide
it from the public. And the money
doesn't just go to real estate
developers. It goes to the dictatorship
itself, at least a good part of it. In
any dictatorship, no company can grow
that big without government approval and
control. If a company in a dictatorship
is massive enough so that it can put up
skyscrapers left and right, then it's
there because the state wants it there.
Dictatorships don't want internal
competition, and dictators [music]
correctly realize that the owners of
large corporations are a potential
threat to their rule. They can become
their rivals if left unchecked. Sure,
the dictator has its army and police,
but what if a billionaire also builds up
its own army and police, and is also in
control of the housing stock? If not
reined in, the billionaire can just
amass enough power and influence over
time anyway to replace the dictator, as
another dictator, of course. This is why
dictators keep billionaires on a very
short leash. For example, at some point
in China, Jack Ma started gaining
prominence. He was a billionaire with
quickly growing social and capital
influence. He then started criticizing
the Chinese government. Xi Jinping had
him disappear immediately. Today, his
companies are run by the Chinese
Communist Party. And my frustration here
is that if dictators realize the threat
of billionaires gaining power and
wealth, how come democratically elected
leaders don't? I've seen so many of them
prostrate themselves in front of
billionaires as if the latter did not
represent an open threat to democracy.
Like in Europe, we wonder about the rise
of far-right propaganda and
misinformation. Meanwhile, half the
freaking media space is run by Axel
Springer, which is controlled by a
pro-AfD billionaire freak. I as I,
Friedrich Merz, right-wing conservative
German chancellor, am very concerned
about the rise of the far right. This is
why I allow half our domestic
media to be run by the far right.
Because what could ever go wrong with
that? Whoops. I have a feeling that our
current leaders just kind of gave up on
the concept of democracy. But while
people like Merz, Starmer, and others
are just pale post-war corpses floating
down the river of history, dictators are
actually proactive in trying to protect
their systems, including by social
engineering done via the ungodly inhuman
projects we've been looking at.
Neighborhoods like these are the
opposite of walkable. You need a car to
get literally anywhere. Roads are
oversized, inhuman, and dangerous. And
crucially, there are very few places
where a lot of people can spontaneously
gather. What, you're all going to walk
out onto the searing hot asphalt sea,
dodging heavy traffic to yell your
slogans? Such areas kill the ability to
socially organize, and they do this on
purpose. Protests against dictatorships
are not centrally organized. They tend
[music] to be spontaneous. It's just
groups of dissatisfied people coming
together in different parts of life
until they sort of connect somewhere.
And suddenly, you have a movement of
tens of thousands of people coming to
throw you out of the palace. In Egypt,
the revolution that took down Hosni
Mubarak had its main support base in
Cairo in an area called the Maspero
Triangle, a very dense, human-scale
neighborhood with narrow streets. This
is where people could organize in secret
against the government. Here, even if
the police come down on you, it's easy
to run and hide. There is a network of
locals who can watch your back, report
on police movements, and there are
millions of places to hide your Molotovs
or to run your little opposition
broadcast and so on. These areas are
great when it comes to opposing a
government. So, no wonder that after
seizing power, one of the first things
the new Egyptian dictator did was to
demolish the entire area. So, what
replaces the Maspero Triangle? No prizes
for guessing this one. Yep, giant
skyscrapers squeezed between giant urban
highways. No more local communities that
could organize. No more chance
encounters with people who have the same
grievances as you. No more ability to
socially organize. No more protests,
which is the whole entire point of it
all. Oh, and also
one of the benefits of dense human-scale
neighborhoods is them being a natural
guard of your privacy. All those little
streets are difficult to surveil, and
even if someone puts up a camera, you
can just throw a brick at it or
something, then disappear into the
alleyways. If a dictator's troops want
to barricade the area, they have to
secure hundreds, if not thousands, of
ways in and out. You need police on
every corner, in every alley,
constantly. Police that the dictator
desperately needs everywhere because
protests are spreading. Now, imagine
people don't live in a dense
neighborhood, but in a giant skyscraper.
Police only need to barricade a few
entrances on the ground floor, and it's
done. You're not going anywhere. The
elevator system is shut down, so if you
want to try and slip through the police
barricade, you will first have to take
the stairs down 80 floors. Police also
know the floor plan of the skyscraper.
All of it was designed centrally, so
they can just start going up floor by
floor. They know who's in the
skyscraper. They know about all the
hiding places. So, they start going up
and drag away all the undesirable
elements to prison. Traditional city
blocks are irregular, chaotic, and
fundamentally human. They are democratic
and anti-authoritarian by nature. Tower
blocks are standardized, regular,
artificial, and fundamentally inhuman.
They are the home turf of any
authoritarian government. They know the
area. They know where you are, or they
know where you could be. They control
your food, water, electricity, heating,
[music] everything. At least in a
traditional block, you can set up a
generator, collect rainwater, have food
smuggled in, and so on. In a tower
block, you are at the dictator's mercy.
And so, you will not rock the boat,
ensuring that the dictatorship survives.
This is why dictatorships look the same.
It's self-preservation, all designed to
alienate people from each other and to
make it easier for police to clamp down
on you. And if dictators go to such
lengths to preserve their systems, why
don't our democratic leaders? Well,
actually, that's a long story. I'll talk
about it in a future video. In the
meantime, thank you for watching. If you
like my content, please consider
becoming a patron or a member here on
YouTube. And I'll be seeing you next
time.